<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truths plea for infants, or, Infants right vindicated in a reply to Jeremiah Ives, chees-munger concerning the baptisme of infants. By Alexander Kellie.</title>
            <author>Kellie, Alexander.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K238A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216626</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828351</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828351</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32778</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47203)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32778)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1951:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truths plea for infants, or, Infants right vindicated in a reply to Jeremiah Ives, chees-munger concerning the baptisme of infants. By Alexander Kellie.</title>
                  <author>Kellie, Alexander.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 24, 33-47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.R. and are to be sold by Nath. Brooks at the Angel in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Ives, Jeremiah.  Infants baptism disproved and believers baptism proved.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ives, Jeremiah, fl. 1653-1674. --  Infants baptism disproved and believers baptism proved --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32778:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TRUTHS PLEA FOR INFANTS, OR, INFANTS RIGHT VINDICATED: In a Reply to <hi>Jeremiah Ives,</hi> Cheeſ-munger concerning the Baptiſme of INFANTS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>ALEXANDER KELLIE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 16.17.</hi>
               </bibl> Now I beſeech you Brethren mark them which cauſe Diviſions and Offences, contrary to the Doctrine which you have learned, and avoid them.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 4.9.</hi>
               </bibl> Theſe things which yee have both learned, and received, and heard, and ſeen in me, do, and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 9.13.</hi>
               </bibl> The Light of the Righteous rejoyceth, but the Candle of the wicked ſhall be put out.</q>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Nath. Brooks</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1656.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32778:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32778:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:32778:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32778:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13.14, 15. hath ſet forth to the life, our Adverſaries with whom we have to do, ſaying, That ſuch are falſe Apoſtles, deceitfull Workers, transforming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt; and no marvell, for Satan him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is transformed into an Angel of Light. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no great thing if his Miniſters alſo be transformed, as the Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, whoſe end ſhall be according to their works. God hath ſeldome, or never, had in any Age his Truth pleaded by his ſervants without the contradiction of his Adverſaries: as 2 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Jannes and Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo our Anabaptiſts reſiſt the Truth, men of corrupt mindes, falſe accuſers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers of thoſe that are good, heady, heigh-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb facs="tcp:32778:4"/>having a forme of godlineſs, but denying the power thereof: but we hope their folly ſhall ſhortly be made manifeſt to all men, that they ſhall proceed no further: They are much like the falſe Prophet <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> In the firſt Book of the <hi>Kings</hi> the laſt Chapter, ver. 24. who ſmote <hi>Miicaiah</hi> the true Prophet, and ſaid, <hi>Which way went the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord from me, to ſpeak unto thee:</hi> all the dirt of foule aſpertions which mine Adverſaries hath caſt upon the Truth, vvhich I have delivered, have not ſo defaced it, but that it can ſufficiently plead for it ſelfe without any further reply, and therefore if I ſhould make no more anſwer then <hi>David</hi> did <hi>Shimei,</hi> or <hi>Ezekiah,</hi> and the men upon the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to the railings of <hi>Rabſhakeh,</hi> the Lord quickly would appeare and plead his own Cauſe with a witneſs againſt his enemies: yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, leſt mine enemies ſhould be too proud, and bragge too much where they have little reaſon; and that my friends ſhould not be led away with the errors of the vvicked, falling from their ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs, and loſing thoſe things vvhich vve have already vvrought, vvherein there is not one vvord to my remembrance that ever I ſpoke in publike ſeverall years againſt the Anabaptiſts, that ever I mind to recall, but if neede be to confirme to the
<pb facs="tcp:32778:4"/>end. And therfore I have once more undertaken to contend for the Truth, which I have not only late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made known here in LONDON, amongſt them that heard me, but hath alſo from <hi>Abrahams</hi> time to Ours been delivered to the Saints. I vvould not have my Hearers, like many of the Anabaptiſts, to caſt away the Helve after the Hatchet, making ſhipwrack of faith and a good conſcience, ſome become Quakers, ſome Ranters, ſome denying God, ſome Chriſt the Lord, againſt Family duties morning and evening, before and after Meate, ſlighting Word and Sacraments, from ſuch the Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p>Finally, Gentle Reader, whereas ſome ſentences in this my Book ſeeme to follow impertinently to what went before, blame not me, but my Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, whom I am to purſue as a theefe, and to ride out of the road way now and then after him vvith Hue and Cry, over ditch and hedge; vvhereas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thervviſe I might have been a great deale more cleare and full, and methodicall.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Houſe in</hi> Giles Criplegate,</dateline>
               <signed>Your Friend in Chriſt, <hi>Alexander Kellie.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:32778:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32778:5"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to the Epiſtle.</head>
            <p>YE are not like the men of <hi>Berea,</hi> but like the Hereticks in all ages, that pretended Scripture for all they ſaid, and there be none more contradictious then you <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> both to all the godly learned in the world, and likewiſe to one another, ſome for the <hi>Glaſs-Houſe,</hi> ſome for <hi>Pauls,</hi> ſome for <hi>Beechlane,</hi> ſome for <hi>Arminians,</hi> ſome against them; and many that frequent one of your places, think it abomination to go to another of them, and many of you are turned <hi>Ranters</hi> and <hi>Quakers.</hi> Sure therefore ye are not like <hi>Solomons</hi> Wiſe men, <hi>Prov. 14.15.</hi> That looke well to their goings; and where you caſt dirt upon the Fathers, you do not ſhew us in what places to finde their errours, and if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re true you ſay of them, yet therein you are more like curſed <hi>Ham</hi> that made knowne his fathers nakedneſs, then like bleſſed <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet,</hi> who hid their faces from it, and covered it. And whereas you look upon us as ſuch who have only the name of Religion, and of Chriſtians, &amp;c. with us, <hi>1 Cor. 4.3.</hi> it is a very ſmall thing that we ſhould be judged of you, who like proud Phariſees deſpiſe us as ſinfull Publicans, and yet I hope we ſhall go away juſtified rather then you. You wickedly ſlander godly learned men, as men minding their profits and credit more
<pb facs="tcp:32778:6"/>then the Truth, whereas there have been, and are, and ſtill will be many hundred thouſand for <hi>Infants Baptiſme,</hi> who never had any worldly profits by it; and where you ſpeak of credit, you ſay true, for a man ſhall have no credit but ſhame before God and man to follow you. Next, you bring in your <hi>Excentriks</hi> and <hi>Epicycles,</hi> and <hi>Phenomina;</hi> ſure Sir, by your high termes you would make ſome ſimple Reader believe that you are ſome great Profeſſour of the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> but your <hi>Phenomina</hi> ſpoiles all, wherein your ignorance of Orthography appears and ſhews plainly that you know no more what an <hi>Eccentricke, Epicycle</hi> or <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> is, then the heele of an old Cheeſe, <hi>Ne ſut or ultra crepidam..</hi> And thus let the unpartiall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Judge juſtly between you and me. And ſo I have done with your Epiſtle, and I come to your Goſpel.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32778:6"/>
            <head>A Reply to <hi>JEREMIAH IVES,</hi> Cheeſe-mungers <hi>Anſwer,</hi> concerning THE BAPTISME OF INFANTS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST, you ſay, Where our Saviour commanded all Nations to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, he meant, not any Infants for four reaſons;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Becauſe they are not then ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of teaching.</item>
               <item>2. All Nations many times do not include Children in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:32778:7"/>3. Becauſe Infidels, Turks, and Children of Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are a great part of all Nations.</item>
               <item>4. Becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is referred to Diſciples. To the firſt I anſwer three things.
<list>
                     <item>1. It is no abſurdity to preach the Goſpel to an Infant, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.70. and ſo on.</item>
                     <item>2. The Apoſtles were to teach all that was command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that could not be done in ſhort time, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by degrees as the party baptized was able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</item>
                     <item>3. The Apoſtles teaching can no more keep back In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants from baptiſme, then <hi>Abrahams</hi> teaching, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 19. could keep back the Infants from Circumciſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17: <hi>v.</hi> 12. To the ſecond I anſwer, yee cite ſome Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of all Nations, but therin you are no Noble <hi>Beraean,</hi> as you would make men believe in the beginning of your Epiſtle, for you give us not one place ſet down where to find the Scriptures. Secondly, You bring us Scriptures for what Infants cannot, to prove that they ſhould not have that which according to Scripture they can have; And wheras you ſay, Infants cannot bleſſe, why is it then ſaid in the 8. <hi>Pſalme, Out of the mouthes of Babes and Suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings thou wilt perfect praiſe,</hi> and in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>48 <hi>Pſ. Praiſe him all people, old men and babes.</hi> Thirdly, J will bring you pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture, where Children are to be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all Nations, which bring them into Baptiſme, more then your Scriptures of all Nations can keep them out; As <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>en.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 13. Where the Lord promiſeth to bleſſe all the Families of the Earth, and their Children are included, and this promiſe of the bleſſing brings them into Baptiſme, more then your Scriptures can hold them out, and withall, this place pronounceth a curſe againſt you Anabaptiſts, for they that curſe <hi>Abrahams</hi> Goſpel
<pb facs="tcp:32778:7"/>way, in ſetting the token of Gods Goſpel-Covenant of grace upon Infants, they curſe <hi>Abraham,</hi> and God hath threatned to curſe ſuch; ſo yee Anabaptiſts are a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration lying under the wrath, and curſe, and vengeance of God.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The other places of Scripture comprehending Infants amongſt all men, and Nations are, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 9. Where it is ſaid, <hi>Chriſt taſted death for every one,</hi> and conſquently for Infants. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 2. Where Chriſt is a propitiation for the whole World, Infants are underſtood, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 5: 18. Which place you grant to be meant of Infants, where it is ſaid, <hi>That the free gift came upon all men unto juſtification of life,</hi> and yet yee will not admit Infants into the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of their firſt entry into any grace. Thirdly, Where you ſay, Turks, Inſidels, and their Children may as well be baptized as Profeſſors Children; it is falſe, for the Infants of Believers are the bleſſed of the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. <hi>v.</hi> 23. They are Gods Children <hi>from the Womb, Ezek.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 20, 21. They are in <hi>Covenant with God, Gen:</hi> 17. And to them <hi>belongs the Kingdome of Heaven:</hi> This is never ſaid of Turks and Infidels; and the Infants of Gods people were by God admitted unto the poſſeſſion of the like Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance to Baptiſme, which God calls the <hi>Token of his Covenant, Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it the <hi>Seal of the Righteouſneſſe of faith, Rom.</hi> 4. and much profitable every way, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. and Infants continued in the poſſeſſion hereof for many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, and the Lord never put them aſide from this long poſſeſſion, no more then he did the aged, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of neceſſity, when he commands all Nations to be baptized, he commands Infants to be baptized. Laſtly, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. you ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt be referred to Diſciples: Sometimes you ſpeak of Children eight daies old, in the Cradle; you can no more then one of them find me in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32778:8"/>the Greek Text a Subſtantive of the Maſeuline Gender to agree with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; but what do J talk of the Greek Text, when you ſhew your ignorance ſo groſſe, as if you had never learned your Accidents, putting a Nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Caſein the Singular Number, for the Accuſative in the Plurall, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and a Noune of your owne deviſing that was never heard of for a Verb, as many times <hi>ſequitor</hi> for <hi>ſequitur,</hi> and ſomtimes a Verb for a Noun, as <hi>Baptizo</hi> for <hi>baptaſmus,</hi> or a Noun again for a Verb, as <hi>Aſperſia</hi> for <hi>aſpergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, J proved Infants were Diſciples, from <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54. <hi>v.</hi> 13. Where the Lord promiſes that Infants ſhall be taught of God, you anſwer, that they are not Diſciples, who do not learn if they were taught: Herein you and Mr. <hi>Tombs,</hi> and the reſt are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earfully out, for <hi>John</hi> 6. <hi>v</hi> 60.66. it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaid, many Diſciples ſaid of Chriſts Doctrine, <hi>This is a hard ſaying, who can heare it?</hi> And they went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from him and would walk no more with him: Here then be Diſciples, and yet they did not learn; you would fain make ſimple people believe that the Moon is made of green Cheeſe, but the Cheeſe munger hath never a Taſter to make us find it ſo. Then you bring in <hi>Jerem.</hi> 32 <hi>v.</hi> 33. Where it is ſaid, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od taught <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but they refuſed to receive inſtruction:</hi> But had not both they and their Infants the Token of Gods Covenant? And did ever any of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſpeak againſt it as a ſin? And is there not moſt gracious promiſes made to the ſame people in the ſame Chapter? As that he would never depart from them to do them good, and that he would put his fear in their hearts that they ſhould never depart from him, and that he would plant them aſſuredly with his whole heart, and with his whole Soul, and yet them you bring in as no Diſciples.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:32778:8"/>In your ſixth page you ſay, Infan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the Cradle are not taught of men, therfore not of God; As if Gods pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſailed in inward teaching, when mans faile in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You ſay, if they were all taught of God, then they ſhould be all ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> So you confeſſe with me, that they are ſaved if they dye in their Infancy, but if after their Infancy they ſhould live and prove bad, yet in the time of their Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy we are to judge charitably, and ſo you are fain to do with them whom yee dip, who afterward prove ſtark naught. Therfore where the Lord promiſeth that all ſhall be taught, Infants muſt be underſtood, otherwiſe yee ſhall leave out a great many of all the Children, for many dye in their Infancy, and are never afterward taught; therfore their teaching muſt be in their Infancy, or elſe never, and if ſo, how ſhall the promiſe be true, <hi>All ſhall be taught:</hi> But ſay you in the ſeventh Page, Why do you teach them to be converted when they come to age. We anſwer, The work of Converſion is the work of a mans whole life. After <hi>Peter</hi> had been converted, Chriſt ſaid to him, <hi>When thou art hereafter converted, ſtrengthen thy Brethren Turn your ſelves and live,</hi> is a Text that may be preached to the beſt Convert ſo long as he lives; but then if men become naught (ſay you) After they have been taught of God. There will be a falling a way from Grace. We anſwer, When we ſay, Infants are taught of God, we mean the elect Infants, who are all taught of God ſooner or latter; but becauſe we cannot ſearch into God ſecrets abſolutely to determine who are elect, and who not, we are charitably to judge the beſt of all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants of Gods people, and if any afterward prove bad, it is but a miſtake in our Judgment, and no change in Gods
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32778:9"/>Election, and yet according to that outward judgment we are to proceed; for when in <hi>John</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 2. our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Every branch in him that bringeth not forth good fruit is out down and caſt in the ſire:</hi> He ſpeaks of Branches that appear ſo to the judgment of men, and yet he calls them Branches in him, ſo we may call Infants Diſciples taught of God, though we have no certainty of every ones particular Election, but a generall ground from the promiſe for our charitable judgment of all.</p>
            <p>In the eighth page you ſay, J ſpeak indiffinitely leaving out the word <hi>All,</hi> J thought you had known that <hi>Indiſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum aequipelet <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſali.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. You ſay, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 1.2. The Lord ſpoke not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> What then, cannot he therfore teach Infants inwardly, inſpiring them with the ſeeds of ſpiritual ſaving truth and life? how came the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſi</hi> to leap for joy in his Mothers Womb at the ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Mary:</hi> And though the Lord ſpoke not to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, yet the Infants had a right to the token of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that then was: And</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yee confeſs that Infants are made righteous by Jeſus Chriſt, and yet formerly you ſaid that in the Command <hi>Baptize all Nati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi> ſuch Infants that are made righteous by Jeſus Chriſt, are no more comprehended then Turks or infidels. You are a ſweet youth. In the ninth page, that which you call a fiction of my brain without one word in all the Bible; to wit, that Infants are inwardly and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually taught or elſe there is no hope of their Salvation. You confeſſed in the ſeventh page, that to be inwardly and effectually taught, was to be really and truly rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated Then I prove what you ſay cannot be found in the Bible: <hi>Except an Infant be born again he cannot enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdome of Heaven, John</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 5. But except an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32778:9"/>be taught effectually of God he cannot be born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, for you confeſſed the new birth to be all one with this teaching, page ſeventh: Therfore except an Infant be effectually taught he cannot enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, neither of Grace nor Glory, for we muſt judge him ſo if he be in the outward Kingdome of Grace, and he muſt be truly ſo a Child of God, taught of God, if he be either truly in grace here, or glory hereafter. If Chriſt bleſſed the Infants, prayed for them, and laid his hands on them, then were they in ſome meaſure capable of his bleſſing and prayer, and the benefit of the laying on of his hands, which could no wiſe be without regeneration and being taught of God, for without it no entry into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, neither of grace nor glory to any purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I will ſhew it by a Golden Scripture Chain. There is no Salvation but by Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 12. but there is no coming to Chriſt but by the Fathers drawing, <hi>John</hi> 6 <hi>v.</hi> 44. But there is no drawing of the Father with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this teaching, <hi>verſe</hi> 45. Therfore without this teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Infants no Salvation, Vertue is ſaid to be copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative; ſo is Grace, ſo is this, having one Link of the Chain you bring all to you.</p>
            <p>Again in the ninth page, you acknowledge from <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 14. That they were Infants of whom Chriſt ſaid, <hi>the Kingdome of Heaven was.</hi> This is more then ever I knew an. Anabaptiſt confeſſe, yet the more baſe you to ſay, that ſuch have no more right to the command of Baptiſme then Turks: Where in the tenth page, you ſay there is eternall life for Infants, without the knowledge of God in Chriſt, it is as much as if you ſaid, Infants have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life without eternal life, for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>This knowledge is eternall life.</hi> Secondly, you ſay there, that Infants that know not the right hand from the left cannot know
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32778:10"/>Chriſt.<note place="margin">Cal. Inſtit. l. <hi>4.16.</hi> ſect. <hi>19.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r non Deus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantibus in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens exigua ſcintilla <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gaiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>? A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b. <hi>ſaith o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Baptiſt,</hi> Habuit intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendi ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſum qui exult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> habuit affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum.</note> J anſwer, We are to believe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God though we do not apprehend them by ſenſe, as you ſeemoſt of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our faith; We beleive them all by faith, though they be far above our ſenſe. The blind man that knew not white from black, yet knew Chriſt to be the <hi>Meſſeas,</hi> the Son of <hi>David,</hi> willing to have mercy on him, and able miraculouſly to cure him: The young Prophets that knew not poyſon from Pot-hearbs, when they put a Goord in the Pot, yet they knew much of the Myſteries of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and they knew the very day when <hi>Elias</hi> ſhould he taken from Earth to Heaven.</p>
            <p>In the eleventh page you ſay, they that know God will truſt in him, and indeed this ſaying is convertible, for they that truſt in God do know him, but Infants truſt in him therfore know him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. And wheras you ſay, there appears as much knowledge of God in a Turks Child as in a Chriſtians, it is falſe, for they have not both the like promiſe; and the profeſſion of the Parents is a ſufficient diſtinguiſhing note, and eſpecially the Text we are handling manifeſteth more in our Children then in Turks.</p>
            <p>That which you ſpeak of Armenianiſme, I have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered already in anſwering to your ſeventh page. Next you bring in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. where it is ſaid, <hi>Without ſaith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> here I make an argument againſt your ſelf. All they that pleaſe God have ſaith, but Infants pleaſe God therfore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the twelfth page you bring in <hi>James</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 17. where he ſaith, <hi>Faith without works is dead,</hi> that place is meant of them that are of age, in whom faith ſhould appear not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32778:10"/>only in the budd and flowers of Profeſſion, but in the Fruit of good works; yet this makes nothing againſt Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in whom faith may be in the ſeed and root. If a Tree have neither leaves, nor bloſſoms, nor fruit in Spring, Summer, nor Harveſt, then it is dead, and yet it may be a good Tree though nothing appear in the firſt of <hi>January.</hi> The reſt that you have in the twelfth page, is nothing upon the matter but what you ſaid, and J have anſwered before.</p>
            <p>In the thirteenth page you cry out of my miſerable blindneſſe, and that J miſerably abuſe the Scriptures, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.20. J am ſure you are a miſerable bold fellow, and they are miſerable blind that follow you for their Guide: If you ſay, that Infants ſhould live a hundred years before they dye a naturall death, you make the Scripture falſe, for Infants do not live ſo long, if you mean their Eſtate in glory, that is likewiſe falſe, for there they do not dye, therfore my ſenſe of the place is better agreeable both to Truth and Text, which ſpeaks both of death and life, and in that ſenſe many ſuch Infants I bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize: But for you Anabaptiſts, you live ſo long old Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples many of you, till yee become more fit for the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be drowned then to be dipped. Yee come in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently with the Midwives ſprinkling on the face. <hi>Amphora caepit institui currente rota cur <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſeus exit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fourteenth page my Maſter <hi>Ives</hi> brings in his <hi>Non ſequitor,</hi> and in that page you ſay, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. God hath preſcribed believing there to be the time of baptizing, it is falſe: And they that gladly received the word, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41. they did not thruſt out Infants that ſhould be ſaved, verſ. 47. from being added to the Church by Baptiſme, wherin God hath not preſcribed any day as in Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to the which <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were then tyed,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32778:11"/>though the Infants had a right to the token from their birth, by vertue of the Covenant, and if there had been no command at all, yet the Covenant brought Infants to Circumciſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. and ſtill gives them a right to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: And though Females were not circumciſed, yet I can give you many Scriptures where Women are reckoned amongſt the Circumciſed. The word Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion includes all the people of Gods Children, and Women, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.30. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.8, 9.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8.9.12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.10. And in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> both men and women were baptiſed Hitherto then it appears that I have not built neither Hay and Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but Truth as Gold, and Pearls upon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.. Now you ſay you will prove my Arguments to be Clouds without water, and yet the firſt is ſuch, that all the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts in <hi>England</hi> cannot anſwer, and ſo are the reſt that follow, let us then try an iſſue.</p>
            <p>God ſaith, <hi>Great ſhall the Childrens Peace be whom he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> You ſay page ſixteen, like a baſe fellow, that God makes but a bare promiſe, but is not ſo good as his word; and where the Text ſpeaks of conferring of peace, you ſpeak of preaching of peace to Infants, the reſt that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes in that page you have it anſwered in the anſwer to the ſeventh page. Wheras you ſay, the Children of the fleſh are not the Children of God: Where the Apoſtle ſeems to ſpeak ſo, he means the fleſh only; But in your ſenſe it is falſe, for many Saints, and holy Kings and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets came of <hi>Abraham,</hi> his Children of the fleſh, and yet they were alſo the precious Children, and we are to look upon all the Children of Gods people as ſuch in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy.</p>
            <p>In the ſeventeenth page, J perceive the Knavery of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titicks, they will ſeem to ſlight that moſt which doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32778:11"/>pinch them hard, ſo he calls my reaſon lighter then If God do not promiſe effectuall teaching to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, then the promiſe <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54. is much one with the threatning, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. which of all the judgments of the world, is one of the ſaddeſt. Though teaching be a mercy as it is tendred to a people, yet it proves a judgment as it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed.</p>
            <p>In the eighteenth page, my place from <hi>John</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 44, 45. is ſo ſtrong for me againſt you, and your anſwer ſo ſhort, weak, and unworthy, that it doth not deſerve a reply.</p>
            <p>In the nineteenth place, the Prophet <hi>Jeremias SHALL,</hi> hath reference to our Goſpel repreſent, wherin that times now w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> before was to come, you are an unworthy man therfore to pronounce a curſe, for that againſt me. You fal foul upon my teaching at <hi>Giles Cripple gate,</hi> and charge them all with folly that pay me a farthing for preaching. J have many loving friends here, and Sir if you had no more for your Cheeſe, then J have of the Pariſh for prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, you would make but a poor Trade of it: You in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed would have all the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> to beg or ſtarve at your doors, <hi>The mercies of the wicked are cruell;</hi> yet the Apoſtle hath ordained that they that preach the Goſpel ſhould live by it; our Saviour ſaith, <hi>The labourer is worthy of his wages,</hi> and they that labour in the word and doctrine, are worthy of double honour. Wheras you ſpeak of going to <hi>America,</hi> better men have gone and do go thither, and are like to do God more ſervice there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Savages then you in <hi>London</hi> amongſt the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts.</hi> But how comes this railing againſt my preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>London,</hi> becauſe <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 11. it is ſaid, <hi>They ſhall not teach every man his Neighbour,</hi> therfore J ſhould not teach; nay, rather you ſhould not teach who have no Goſpel or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, but like Theeves and Robbers, ye come not in at
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32778:12"/>the door but as it were through Walls, and over Hedges. The Negative is not abſolute but Comparative, for it is men ſhall not be ſo much taught of men as of God, and ſo it is unpertinently brought in againſt me, you could hit better upon this diſtinction of Negatives in my houſe, though you came untowardly to it; for when our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Heath</hi> told you that <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſent to Baptize but to Preach, you Anſwered, he was not ſo much ſent to to Baptize; but before that, you ſaid a man ſhould not Preach except he be ſent, but he may Baptize, ſaid you, without Commiſſion, why then do you require a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for Baptizing of Infants, and why do you Preach and are not ſent? Let me aske you, how can ſuch as you go to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, ſith the Lord hath forbid ſuch to come to the Paſsover, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. v. 48. Where if he that circumciſed not his child might not eat of the Paſsover, then he that doth not Baptize his child muſt not eat of the Lords Supper. And if <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt not ſuffer them to live with him that did not Circumciſe their Infants, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. v, 13. Then Chriſtians if they have a lawfull power in their hands, ſhould not ſuffer Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts to live with them becauſe they refuſe to Baptize their <hi>Infants.</hi> And if the ſoule was cut off that was not Circumciſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. v. 14. And God ſought to kill <hi>Moſes</hi> for the neglect of Circumciſion., <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 24. how much more then damnably dangerous is the willfull neglect of Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>In the twentieth page I Said, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 9. that children truſt in God. Ye Anſwer hereto the words (when I was) are unnecſſarily put in, yet otherwiſe ye cannot make ſenſe of it. And ye ſay <hi>David</hi> in his infancy, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently Chriſt whom the <hi>Pſalm.</hi> chiefly concernes, did not more hope in God from the mothers breaſt then
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32778:12"/>unbelievers children; and you ſay the whole Creation is ſubjected in hope then by you, the hope of Chriſt, of <hi>David,</hi> and the children of Gods people is all one with the hope of a Snake or a Toad, O baſe blalphemy. Laſtly, <hi>Tremelius</hi> that knows the Originall better then you Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlates the Hebrew word <hi>Confidere,</hi> which is to truſt, and more then the ordinary hope of the creature.</p>
            <p>And to the one and twentieth page, I Anſwer, the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of children is Gods inſpired Grace which goeth with his inward and effectuall teaching, which is more then the innocency of Doves, or wiſdome of Serpents, for <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 4. they that are ſo humble are ſaid to be the greateſt in the Kingdome of heaven, but it is not ſo with the Doves innocency, or Serpents wiſdom; a man may have the Doves innocency, to do no man wrong, yet go to hell becauſe he doth no man good, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25. and a man may have the Serpents wiſdome and be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and want that wiſdome as children do and be ſaved; but this humility is ſuch, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. <hi>v</hi> 3 that there is no heaven without it, and the greateſt happineſs of heaven comes by it, <hi>v.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>In the two and twentieth page, I Anſwer, conferre <hi>Eſay</hi> 54. <hi>v.</hi> 13. with 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10. In the firſt you finde Gods teachings of all his peoples children, in the latter, that this teaching is effectuall, therefore it will follow, that childrens teaching being the teaching of God is ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall.</p>
            <p>To the three and twentieth page I Anſwer, though ſome be not called till the laſt hour, yet we muſt judge the beſt of them, according to their outward Church priviledges and faederall rights.</p>
            <p>To the four and twentieth page I anſwer, Profeſſion was as much required of <hi>Abraham</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32778:13"/>yet that did not debarre <hi>Infants</hi> from Circumciſion, nor can it now from Baptiſme.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You come with a fallicie in the word <hi>(name)</hi> for in the Kings name, may be in the Kings Authority, and to ſhew favour in God or Chriſts Name, is for God or Chriſts ſake, but any man ſees that to give to a Prophet, in the name of a Prophet, and to a righteous man in the name of a righteous man, and to a child in the name of a Diſciple, is to give to them as to Prophets and righteous men as to Diſciples.</p>
            <p>To the five and twenty page I anſwer I do keep me to <hi>Infants</hi> of Profeſſors, and ſuch were they, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.10. <hi>for Chriſt was not ſent but to the loſt ſheepe of Iſrael,</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed themſelves the people of God, and whoſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren had received the token of the Covenant of God.</p>
            <p>To the twenty ſixth page I Anſwer, the unprofitable ſervant was able to worke and would not, but the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren cannot, yet God calls them his ſervants.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If unprofitable ſervants be not ſervants, why are they called ſervants? and if not ſervants, then none of Chriſts Diſciples are ſervants, for when we have done all we can, we are unprofitable ſervants, the beſt of us ye have up with your <hi>non ſequitor, ſequetor</hi> againe.</p>
            <p>Againe, you cite the Text which I bring (you ſay) falſely, to wit, <hi>Levit.</hi> 21. for 25. <hi>v.</hi> 41, 42. where any man of the world may ſee that Infants are underſtood, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you ſay, for they were not to be left behind as bond-ſlaves, you are fearefully out in ſaying that ſuch were never at ſuch age ſervants as appears by <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.7. where <hi>Salomon</hi> had them that were born ſervants in his houſe, if born ſervants then ſo in the cradle. Now I come to the 15. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> where <hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>Infants</hi> Diſciples, <hi>v.</hi> 10. where you ſay, the yoke upon the neck of the Diſciples is as a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32778:13"/>taxe upon the Clergie, as it will not follow (ſay you) all the Clergy are taxed, therefore all that are taxed are Clergy men, ſo then your Diſciples that can anſwer for themſelves are your Clergy men, for whom only the Apoſtle pleads, ſay you; then if believers <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> be they that have this taxe upon them, which is the yoke of Circumciſion, and if the Apoſtle ſpeake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for them as being none of your Clergy Diſciples, then it will follow that believers <hi>Infants</hi> muſt ſtill be Circumciſed, vvhy then do not you circumciſe your children for they are none of the Clergy Diſciples, for vvhoſe freedome only you vvould have the Apoſtle plead. Then ye give a touch to the Doctrine that vvas taught the Brethren, as if that had been the only yoke vvhich is apparantly falſe, for it is cleare when the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles oppoſed Circumciſion, they oppoſed not only the falſe Doctrine of it, but alſo the continuance of the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Circumciſion it ſelfe: And you ſay you can read, Read then the firſt verſe of the Chapter, vvhere you find Circumciſion after the manner of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and all know that vvas the Circumciſion of <hi>Infants;</hi> this the Apoſtle calls a yoke upon the neck of the Diſciples. Therefore <hi>Infants</hi> are diſciples; or thus, they for whoſe freedome <hi>Peter</hi> pleads, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. are diſciples; But <hi>Peter</hi> pleads for <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> therefore they are diſciples; I prove <hi>Peter</hi> pleads for them, becauſe he pleads for the ſame for whom <hi>Paul</hi> pleads; but <hi>Paul</hi> pleads for the children, <hi>Acts</hi> 21. <hi>v.</hi> 21. therefore <hi>Peter</hi> alſo here pleads for them</p>
            <p>In the twenty eight page, What I ſpeake of <hi>Infants</hi> ignorance, I ſpeake <hi>conceſſione fiduciaria,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, you know my meaning, for you Sir are no praevarica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, but a Clergyy Diſciple, and may commence Doctor when ye will.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:32778:14"/>2. I ſay the command of <hi>Infants</hi> Circumcſion includes them in the command of Baptiſme, for if by Gods Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and command they were in the long poſſeſſion of an Ordinance ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivolent to Baptiſme, and never afterward put from Baptiſme, they muſt needs be included in the Command, and ſo the queſtion is not begged, he that beggs at your door ſhall find poor reliefe. Againe, the faith of Parents profeſſing ſuffices to bring in the children.</p>
            <p>In the twenty ninth page, I ſay that Babes ſprinkled feele the vvater as truly as <hi>Peter</hi> felt the waſhing, and vvhen Chriſt waſhed, Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Peter,</hi> knew not vvhat he did, yea, he knew no more the end and uſe of it at that time then an Infant; yea, he oppoſed it more then an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant could have done, for at the firſt he would not ſuffer Chriſt to do it, yet then ſaid Chriſt it muſt be done; and it vvas ſufficient that <hi>Peter</hi> might know it thereafter, and ſo it is with <hi>Infants</hi> Baptiſme: and whereas you ſay, that <hi>Peter</hi> was ignorant but of a circumſtance, ye are farre out, for Chriſt ſaid that he was ignorant of the worke: which Chriſt wrought, and you ſay he was ignorant of the end and uſe of it, and is the work, the end, and the uſe nothing but a circumſtance; and why do you deny children being ignorant of ſuch a circumſtance.</p>
            <p>In the thirtieth page, you come impertinently in with baptizing of Bells and going a Pilgrimage, and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſing the ſixt or fourth day, and giving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Bread and Wine to <hi>Infants,</hi> ſaying that ſuch things are not forbidden: For I Anſwer, though ſuch things were never forbidden in Scripture, yet the like was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver commanded but for children as Baptiſme is not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden them, ſo the like Ordinance was commanded them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:32778:14"/>In the one and thirtieth page, You ſay the Eunuch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, therefore <hi>Infants</hi> ſhould not be Baptiſed, what poor ſtuffe here is? I ſhall Anſwer the 16. of <hi>Marke</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Againe, I ſay the excluding of not underſtanding diſciples puts not children more aſide from Baptiſm then 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 10. The excluding of them that do not worke puts children aſide from the Breaſt: And then in the two and thirtieth page you ſay, If children will not worke they muſt not eate. I wonder what great will any <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant</hi> hath to worke and yet if need be ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved of the Churches charity, and there lieth as great a charge upon Parents to Baptize their children as to feed them.</p>
            <p>In the thirtieth third page, Ye ſay, when all Nations ſhall be ſeparated good from bad, you ſay <hi>Infants</hi> are not underſtood there, becauſe it cannot be ſaid to them, <hi>When I was hungry ye feed me, &amp;c.</hi> then by your Opinion they are not to be ſeparated from the Goates, but muſt go to hell with them, and yet you ſaid before they were all ſaved. That which you talke of knowing right hand and left is anſwered already, ye make a wofull Text of that 25. of <hi>Matth.</hi> againſt <hi>Infants,</hi> as ye begin to apply it, for they neither feed, nor viſit, nor cloth more then the Goates; but the truth of the Text is, the <hi>Infants</hi> are reckoned with the Parents, what the Parants do, it is as if the Infants had done it. When the wicked world was drowned, the Parent and the Infants were drowned, ſo when <hi>Sodom</hi> was burnt, and ſo when <hi>Pharoah</hi> and his hoaſt were drowned; and when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was ſaved, they and their little ones were ſaved.</p>
            <p>I come to the thirty fourth page, where ye deny my whole argument, And I ſay, that he who denies what that Argument containes, be he who he will, had never
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32778:15"/>the fear of God in his heart, for he that fears God dare not deny <hi>Infants</hi> Baptiſm, knowing that God had given them a right to a priviledge of an Ordinance aequivalent, and though he take away the Ordinance, yet he never took away the priviledges, whereof this is one, that they ſhould have ſome token of his Covenant and we know none now for firſt admiſſion but Baptiſme.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They that had a right to Circumciſion have a right to Baptiſme, that follows it, for the people of God are not put aſide from keeping our Sunday for the Saboath day, becauſe the Saturday which they were to keep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is taken away; and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Epheſs.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3. the fifth Command is a command with Promiſe of a bleſſing in the Land where ever obedient children lives, though now the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> which in the Comand was promiſed be in the <hi>Turks</hi> Poſſeſſion, even ſo the taking away of Circumciſion puts children rather in the poſſeſſion of Baptiſme then takes it from them; what ye write of Duke, <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and the like ſhewes your vanity, whereas you ſpeake of umbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> they are not to be compared to beleeving Chriſtians, for in the <hi>Romanes</hi> God hath cut them and their children off from being his branches in the Olive.</p>
            <p>I am now come to your abſurdities in the thirty ſixt p. in one place you ſpeak of a diſcent from <hi>Abraham,</hi> where any one but a Blockhead may know that the word comes from <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcendo,</hi> and not from <hi>diſcendo;</hi> Circumciſion was a yoak in the cutting off the fleſh, and tying people to a keeping of the whole Law, but the advantage of it, for <hi>Infants</hi> is ſtill continued in Baptiſme, though the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhip of Circumciſion be gone, yet the advantage re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines. Ye give a ſtout hallenge to me and to all the world to ſhew one Text, threatning Parents for not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32778:15"/>Baptizing their <hi>Infants.</hi> I have ſhewed you that the Lord met <hi>Moſes</hi> to kill him for not Circumciſing his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, Exo.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 24. And <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. the Lord commands to cut off the uncircumciſed <hi>Infants,</hi> And our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>Except we be borne againe of water, we cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into heaven;</hi> and <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 23. The Apoſtle ſaith, That we cannot eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſalvation, and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 28, 29. He that deſpiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> Law died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy, of how much ſorer puniſhment ſhall he be thought worthy who hath troden under foot the Son of God, and hath counted the blood of the Covenant wherewith he is ſanctified an unholy thing, and hath done deſpite to the Spirit of Grace, as now Anabaptiſts do, in neglicting, ſlighting, mocking and oppoſing <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> Baptiſme; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 8. That Chriſt ſhall appeare in flaming fire, taking vengeance of ſuch as you that do not obey the Goſpel of our Lord, And our Saviour was much diſpleaſed for keeping <hi>Infants</hi> from him.</p>
            <p>In the thirty ſeven page, I ſay, whereas our Saviour ſaith, <hi>That the Phariſees were of their Father the Devil,</hi> and they that offered up their children to the devill, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. <hi>v.</hi> 37. were no better; and they in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 20. were ſuch, yet God call their children his, and they had his token which <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 3. advantaged much every vvay, and now ye will have children have no token ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious any vvay, therefore ye make them vvorſe now then the children of the devils ſervants were then.</p>
            <p>In the thirty eight page, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. <hi>v.</hi> 20. Propheſieth, that children in Goſpel times ſhall have all Goſpel Privilled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, vvhereof the token of his Covenant is one as much as ever before, though the legality of Circumciſion be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32778:16"/>taken away. And <hi>Mich.</hi> 7. laſt, and <hi>Luk</hi> 1.71, 72. The truth vvhich God ſweare to <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Fathers, and vvhich Chriſt came to fulfill, belonged to the Parents and their <hi>Infants,</hi> and vvas ſealed to both of them by Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and to us and ours by Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>To the thirty ninth page, God commands our <hi>Infants</hi> to be Baptized, when he ſaith, <hi>Baptize all Nations, Matth.</hi> 28. And vvhen <hi>Peter,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be Baptized every one, for the Promiſe is made to your children,</hi> and <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. When God ſaith, <hi>My token ſhall be upon your children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the forty page, I ſay, the children of the <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> were not all one; we deſire but the favour the Heathen had, who when they confeſſed their Lord to be their God had Gods Seale upon their <hi>Infants.</hi> I have anſwered already all in the one and forty page, only where ye ſay, that Baptiſme is not a Seale, therein ye make it worſe then Circumciſion, which the Apoſtle calls, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. the Seale of Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>To the forty thrid page, you ſaid Baptiſme was the Ordinance profitable every way; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that Circumciſion is ſuch therefore upon the matter you made Baptiſme and Circumciſion all one, and yet ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted your ſelfe in ſaying afterwards they were no wiſe paralel; Sir, there were no gentlemen in my houſe that favour your Error for all your Logick, except the Anabaptiſts whom ye brought along with you.</p>
            <p>To the forty foure page, I ſay God himſelf makes it an Argument from his Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. to the token upon the children, as it appers by the word <hi>therefore,</hi> in the 9. <hi>v.</hi> God <hi>gives</hi> us not ſuch an Argument for Will-Worſhip. Ye ſay, if I look <hi>Deut.</hi> I. <hi>v.</hi> 39. where I lookt I found no Covenant at all. The place is <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 1. And the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant the Lord made when they came out of <hi>Egypt</hi> is the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32778:16"/>ſame with this in <hi>Deut.</hi> when they were to enter into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> it was the ſame in ſubſtance, but dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering in circumſtances. In <hi>Deut.</hi> it was made to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren when they were to enter in to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> In <hi>Exod.</hi> it was made with the Parents forty years before when they came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Covenant then was the ſame in the matter of it, but it differed in the time place, and perſons with whom it was made.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ye ſay, that the Covenant in <hi>Deut.</hi> is another, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that when they came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> vvhen the Lord gave them the Law, in the ten Commandements. There can be but two Covenants, <hi>viz:</hi> of Works, or of Grace. But vvhat ever you may think that they were two Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants differing eſſentially, yet in truth they were both of Grace, for vvhen the people came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Lord was a Husband to them in that Covenant, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it vvas a Covenant of Grace, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. <hi>v.</hi> 32: And the Covenant in <hi>Deut.</hi> The Apoſtle calls it the righteouſneſs of Faith, therefore the Covenant of Grace alſo.</p>
            <p>Craftily ye bid compare the 10 and 12. <hi>Verſes</hi> of the 29. <hi>Chapter</hi> of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> leaving out the 11. between them, becauſe it is full againſt you and the Covenant of Grace is one and the ſame though it be many times renued.</p>
            <p>Next we come to the forty fifth page, In handling the Covenant you ſhew your ſelfe groſly ignorant, and know not what ye ſay, yet ye would have m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> believe whatever ye ſay, but when your Noſe is Cheeſe the Cats ſhall eat it. In theſe times and places wherein we live, God hath done vvonderfull things, yet vve have been ſo unthankfull and unfruitfull, that vve have not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32778:17"/>yet had hearts to perceive, nor eyes to ſee to this day, and yet we are not Infidells, ſo it vvas vvith the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in ſuch a caſe, they ſtill believed the Lord to be their God. <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 8. doth not allude to <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 4. but to <hi>Eſa.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 10. that ſin vvas growing upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> time, but it came not to a full ripeneſs till the Apoſtles time, for before they were lookt upon as branches in the Olive, but then cut off. The vvorſt Parents whoſe children I Baptize are ſounder in the faith then the beſt Anabaptiſte vvith you, ſo you are rotten Heriticks. The very ſame men whom you call unbelievers, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 30. <hi>v.</hi> 14. ſaith, <hi>The word was very nigh unto them in their mouth, and in their heart that they might do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This word being in the heart of the Parents to believe it, and in their mouth to confeſs it ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the little ones into Covenant with God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12. This way the Apoſtle calls <hi>the righteouſneſs of faith, Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 6. and this he Preached <hi>v.</hi> 8. Therefore the Fathers faith and Confeſſion muſt ſtill enter the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Covenant with God, which cannot now be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Baptiſme, which is the initiating token of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Sir, It is one thing to be in Covenant, which I proved firſt, and another thing yet conſequently follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have the token of the Covenant which the femalls were not capable of in Circumciſion, as now in Baptiſme, as <hi>Acts</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 12. And Gods Argument is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for <hi>Infants</hi> right to the token from the Covenant, and though then he prefixed a certaine time, yet it was ſtill in their infancie, and ſo ſtill now in <hi>Infancie</hi> where we have no prefixed time.</p>
            <p>Thus to your forty ſeven page; but before I come to the forty eight, I muſt remember ſome good ſtuffe in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32778:17"/>forty ſixt, where you ſay you are relieved from deſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of me by a Latine Sentence, which is <hi>Opere in longo, &amp;c.</hi> and it ſpeaks of ſleepe, and you of deſpare: O brave Clarke, you underſtand your Latine well, and apply it better, but do not ſleep yet, up run <hi>Robbin</hi> the Ram is in the Rye: the Propheſie in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.25. is to children, and to childrens children, and that for ever; and the Lord ſaith, <hi>He will ſet his tabernacle amongſt them,</hi> which muſt be his out ward Ordinance, now children can have no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ordinance if Baptiſme be denied. Where you bring in <hi>Noah,</hi> it is to no purpoſe. Where ye ſay I may as well ſay a childe is Chriſt as Baptize it; if you mean Chriſt perſonally ye ſpeak blaſphemy, if ye meane Chriſt col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectively with his members, Chriſt then is ſo taken in Scripture as I <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>Ye have abundance of Non ſenſe in the forty nine page, to which I Anſwer, Baptiſme was never ordained for Angels as for <hi>Infants,</hi> and the Apoſtles being once recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the Church needed not to be twiſe Baptized, and ſo be <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fifty page, Ye ſay no man denies that they were <hi>Infants</hi> whom Chriſt bleſſed when he tooke them in his Arms. I never knew an <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> confeſs it before, and theſe <hi>Infants</hi> had that from Chriſt which was better then all you can make of your dipping, and yet they believed and underſtood and confeſſed as little, being, as you ſay, <hi>Infants,</hi> as they do now at Baptiſm; and here we find that Chriſt laid his hands upon them, but no where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Supper: and what ye ſpeak of teaching, I have Anſwered already, and if you were ingenuous, where one Reaſon doth not ſeem to give you ſatisfaction, take in my other reaſons with it, and then a threefold cord is not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily broken, <hi>Nam quae quod non proſunt ſingula multa juvent,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:32778:18"/>where you ſay, Jeſus Baptized none, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 1. it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared he did Baptize. Chriſt is ſaid to do what the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did by his Command, as <hi>Peter</hi> may be ſaid to have Baptized <hi>Corneliouſſes</hi> houſe, though the Text only ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 48. that he commanded them to Baptized. <hi>Infants</hi> have a right to all the priviledges of the Church, and to the Kingdome of heaven, but that right is as by reverſion, but they have a right to Baptiſme in their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant</hi> injoyment.</p>
            <p>To the fifty ſecond p. As the <hi>Jewes</hi> were cut off, the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles</hi> were ingrafted, but the <hi>Jewes</hi> vvhen they ſtood, or vvere cut off, or ſhall be reſtored, both they and their children were ſo, and ſo it is with the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the fifty third page, I ſay all that are of the fleſh, are not truly begotten of God, and yet many after the fleſh were after the Spirit alſo, nevertheleſs all of them in out ward Church priviledges, and though a great many of them be caſt into out ward darkneſe, yet are to be lookt upon as the children of the Kingdome, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 12. All that had the token of Gods Covenant were reckoned as <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed in Covenant, but ſuch were not only the children of the fleſh in outward priviledges, but the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> alſo of the Proſelites after the fleſh, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently our <hi>Infants</hi> being Gods people by Nature, and not ſinners of the <hi>Gentiles, Gal.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 15. but <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 16. the Apoſtle calls this ſeed Chriſt, therefore members of Chriſt, therefore ver. 27. fit to have Chriſt put on them by Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>To the fifty fourth page, The vvives ſanctification, and the holines of the childe differ; the child is holy faede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally by the Covenant with the believing Parent, but the unbelieving wife is ſet apart for the ſanctified cohabita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the believing husband with her. Unbelievers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:32778:18"/>married, their marriage is lawfull but not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 15. but if the one be a believer, though the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be not, yet the marriage is ſanctified to the believer, and lawfull to both, ſo ſhe is but ſanctified, as the Apoſtle ſpeakes 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5. As for <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.15. I do not ſo much miſtake the place, as I perceive ye donot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> did according to <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.24. deſtroy the Infants which were a part of the holy people, ye reaſon wildly when you ſay they could not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed with the holy people, becauſe they could not be ſaid to have power vvith them, <hi>vid.</hi> 1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>To the fifty five page, <hi>Repent</hi> is a command of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Tence, vvhich they that vvere Baptized then, were to performe afterward, as <hi>John</hi> Baptized to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The children are brought in in the Promiſe beſides them that vvere charged to repent. And why not the <hi>Infants</hi> of the cradle under Chriſts vvings? ye believe your Infants are not under Gods protection. What a mad Argument had this been of the Apoſtle, to ſay ye have good reaſon to be Baptized, for now it is a great deale worſe vvith your children then it was before, for before the Lord vvas their God, vvherein all the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Promiſes that may be are contained, but now they have none, before they had a token but none now, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you have good hearting to be Baptized; here had been fearfull mad motives to encourage them. The <hi>Jews</hi> ſaid, Chriſts blood be upon us and ours; this blood <hi>Peter</hi> ſo applied it, that it melted the hearts of his Hearers; now to comfort them againe, he ſaith, <hi>The Promiſ is made to you and your children.</hi> This had beene but cold comfort to ſay you prayed that Chriſts blood might be on your Infants, and now I tell you the Promiſe doth not belong
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:32778:19"/>to them. By children, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>Infants</hi> are underſtood firſt, becauſe the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which moſt uſually ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth <hi>Infants:</hi> Secondly, the children are ſet down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides them that underſtood what he ſpake, and beſides them that were called, or to be called a farre of, and and if Infants be not in the Promiſe, what becomes of them when they die, or what are they better then than Infidells children? And the Apoſtle ſpeaks indefinitly of all, leaving out no <hi>Infants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the fifty ſixt page, The Fathers were Baptized, not in <hi>Moſes</hi> name but in Gods name, yet to <hi>Moſes</hi> as their guide before them, and as the water in <hi>Jordan</hi> was Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall water only to them that were Baptized by <hi>Iohn</hi> and his Diſciples in it, but not to the Cattell that went thorow it; ſo the Baptiſme in the red Sea was Baptiſme to the Fathers, and not to the beaſts, though you make it alike to both.</p>
            <p>To the fifty ſeven page, Your contumelious reproaches againſt me, are more fit for ſuch a fellow as you to utter then me to anſwer. I take a Prevaricator to be he that handles a good cauſe badly, and then though I handle it badly, yet ye are baſe to oppoſe a good cauſe; and what you mocked, I ſay it againe and againe. That what was commanded by Chriſt was taught and practiſed by the Apoſtles: it was practiſed, for they were not like the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees that taught one thing and did another. And what was commanded was taught by them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. elſe they ſhould prove worſe then the <hi>Centurions</hi> ſervants who obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Maſter. Now Chriſt commanded that they ſhould ſuffer little ones to come to him that they might fully every way have as much done to them as Baptiſme comes to; therefore the Apoſtles in their practiſe could never ſcruple <hi>Infants</hi> Baptiſme; ye talke like an Aſs in bringing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32778:19"/>in the inſtance of an Aſs. It vvas neceſſary that that of the Aſs ſhould be once done to fulfill the Propheſie, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. but this of <hi>Infants</hi> hath a reaſon of perpetuall ſtanding for the continuance of it, vvhich is becauſe to ſuch belongs the kingdome of heaven.</p>
            <p>To the fifty eight page, Some receiving of the Word, doth not exclude <hi>Infants</hi> from Baptiſme, for by men and women, males, and females are underſtood taking in <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> in the number, ſo our Saviour calls a new born child a man, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Cornelius</hi> and <hi>Lydia</hi> were ſuch as ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the true God, and though <hi>Gentiles</hi> borne, yet when their houſes vvere Baptized the priviledges of a Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite belonged to them and their <hi>Infants,</hi> to be in Covenant with God, and to have the token upon both, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whether there vvere <hi>Infants</hi> in their houſes or not, it matters not, but upon that account if there had been a thouſand, they had all been Baptized.</p>
            <p>In the fifty ninth page, It is a fooliſh reaſon for you to ſay <hi>Infants</hi> in <hi>Stephans</hi> houſe could not adminiſter to the Saints, therefore they ſhould not be Baptized, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 33. <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaks of the Jaylors houſe, according to their capacitie: when he ſpeakes of all hearing and believing the Word, he meanes ſuch as were able, and vvhen he ſpeaks of Baptiſme, he means likewiſe ſuch as are able to receive it, which <hi>Infants</hi> are; <hi>Lydia</hi> might have children for ought as you know, and might have a husband then alſo, for all you can bring to the contrary.</p>
            <p>In the ſixty firſt page, I do inſtance women at the Lords Supper, intending to deny no thing I have ſaid, but it is <hi>argumentum ad hominem,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>quiſque</hi> may be where there is no woman, therfore they do not prove women at the Lords Supper from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</p>
            <p>In the fixty ſecond page, The Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12. to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32778:20"/>ſtop the mouthes of falſe Apoſtles that were for Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, ſaith, <hi>We are Circumciſed in Baptiſme,</hi> now if Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme did not reach <hi>Infants</hi> as well as Circumciſion did, then the loſs in regard of <hi>Infants</hi> is more by the want of Circumciſion then our gaine is by having of Baptiſme, and ſo the falſe Apoſtles might have ſaid our loſſes are not fully made up by Baptiſme, and ſo Baptiſme cannot give us ſatisfaction for our loſs. And where you ſay <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> Circumciſion did not ſignifie the hearts Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; it is falſe, for it was a token that the Lord was the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> God, which containeth all Gods Promiſes, whereof this is one, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. <hi>I will Circumciſe thy heart and the heart of thy children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſixty third page, You complaine that my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have not water enough to ſprinkle a child: it is no matter if they be weighty, though they be not watery. I grant yours are watery enough to plunge over head and eares, and you and all your Arguments like <hi>Ruben</hi> light as water, as water put it in a round glaſs it is round, put it in a ſquare glaſs it is ſquare, put it in a green, blew, or yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low glaſs, its like the glaſs, ſo you conform to the times, ſome times Quaquers, or Seekers, Antinomians, Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Socinians, Anabaptiſts, or what ye will.</p>
            <p>Theſe men whom I name, page fifty three, could do little good upon the obſtinacy that were in the Times and Places where they lived Therefore I have little hopes to do good upon you. The Authors I name are for the Word, and you like an erroneous fellow are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inſt it.</p>
            <p>In the ſixty foure page, you come to your proof of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Baptiſme; but who denies it, you ſhould have proved that they that were Baptized in their infancy muſt be Baptized againe, when they can make you a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32778:20"/>with underſtanding, and you have no ſhew for that, but <hi>Acts</hi> 19. where the Diſciples were not Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized againe of <hi>Paul,</hi> but only <hi>Paul</hi> tells how they had been Baptized of <hi>Iohn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſixty fifth page, You bring in <hi>Marke</hi> 16.16. which place is no rule to us for Baptiſme, for it ſpeaks of ſaving faith, and ſuch as was accompanied with mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, but ſuch faith we cannot now finde out in any; the Text only ſhews who then were in the way of ſalvation. <hi>John</hi> preached Baptiſme unto Repentance, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. which after ward was to follow and ſo ſutes Infants. The Word <hi>We</hi> doth include and not exclude Infants, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. neither doth the confeſſion of aged, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. hinder the Baptiſme of <hi>Infants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſixty ſixt page, You come to prove Dipping, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which I ſind ſorty times in the four Goſpels, and twenty times in the <hi>Acts,</hi> and above half a ſcore of times in <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, beſides <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which I finde twenty ſixe times in the New Teſtament, yet in all theſe places the word cannot appear once to ſignifie Dipping over Head and Eares. But I confeſs I know not where <hi>Baptizo</hi> ſignifies <hi>Aſperſio,</hi> for the one is a Verbe, and the other is a Noune, but my man knows not a Verbe from a Noune, yet I can ſhew where <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are put for <hi>aſperſiones,</hi> as <hi>Heb</hi> 9.10. compared with theſe ſame Verſes in the ſame Chapter, to wit, 13, 19, 21. And all Grace is ſignified by ſprinkling, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. <hi>&amp;c</hi> where ſprinkling with cleane water ſignifies cleanſing from all filthineſs, and a new heart, and a new ſpirit, and a put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Gods Spirit in that new heart and ſpirit, cauſing it to walke in, and to keep and do all Gods Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and to ſave it from all future uncleaneſs; what can the heart of man deſire more then is here ſignified by
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:32778:21"/>the ſprinkling of water, and in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. by ſprinkling is meant the hearts through cleanſing; So <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. Chriſts blood is called the blood of ſprinkling, which is no leſs then 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7. then a cleanſing from all ſin. You cite for Chriſts Baptiſme over head and eares, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16 3. where we have nothing but a foule weather morning, as your Pamphlet is full of dirt and mire and bluſtring wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the place is <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.16. where the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>from the water,</hi> nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>out of the water,</hi> then <hi>Marke</hi> 1.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is put for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is <hi>in,</hi> is put for <hi>with</hi> or <hi>by, Mat.</hi> 6.29.11.21. Chap. 16.27. Chap. 25.31. <hi>Ioh</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 4.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.13.2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. and ſo makes nothing to your purpoſe. Next you ſay <hi>Iohn</hi> was Baptized in <hi>Aenon;</hi> it is more then ever I read or heard any man of the world ſay before you that will ſay any thing, yet ye cite for it, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.23. where there is never a word of <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſme, nor of no bodies elſe; the place you meane is 3.23. where it is to be obſerved that <hi>Aenon</hi> is a Brook that you may ſtep over with your foote, therefore though it had much wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ſprinkling, it had not enough for dipping; and when <hi>Philip</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch</hi> went down from the Chariot and upper ground to the water below them, it is not ſaid they went over head and eares, without which they might come both from and out of the water.</p>
            <p>In the old Teſtament the Hebrew for Dipping it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſometime ſignifieth dying with colours, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.15. and ſometimes drowning, as <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.4. This the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> will not like, though it ſets forth an outward conformity to the death and buriall of Chriſt more then dipping, and yet they urge a neceſſity of dipping rather then ſprinkling, becauſe of this outward conformity; and ſometimes I confeſs the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word doth ſignifie Dipping, but not a whole Plunging of the thing dipt, as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32778:21"/>
               <hi>Levit.</hi> 14.6. where the living Bird, the Ceder Wood, and the Scarlot, were all of them dipt in the blood of one little Bird, vvhich could not be by plunging all in ſo little a quantity of blood; and in the 15. and 16. verſes of the ſame Chapter. the Prieſt was commanded to dip his right ſinger in the Oyle that vvas powred in the palm of his left hand, which could be no more then the top of his finger; and <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 3.13. it is ſaid only the ſoles of the Prieſts feete vvere in the water vvhen they dipt in <hi>Jordan, v.</hi> 15. and <hi>Ruth</hi> is ſaid to dip her Bread in the Vinegar, <hi>Ruth</hi> 2.14. though ſhe put but a little in it; and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14 is ſaid to dip his Rod, vvhen he put forth only the end of it into the Hony Comb. Therefore I conclude, that neither the <hi>Hebrew</hi> vvord for dipping in the Old, nor the <hi>Greeke</hi> in the New will ſignifie a plunging of the vvhole neceſſarily.</p>
            <p>Now let unbiaſſed men judge how little all this makes for dipping. Next ye bring in <hi>Socrates Hiſtoricus,</hi> whom you call <hi>Scholaſticus</hi> relating the Baptiſme of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great. I Anſwer, it is a Queſtion vvhether ever <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> vvas Baptized at all. As for moſt of your Church Hiſtory Writers, it is vvell known to the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned how falſe and fabulous they are. <hi>Carolus Sigonius lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de Occidentis Imperio ad An.</hi> 350 ſaith, <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtantinus &amp; Constants utrumne ſacro fonte abluti vita exceſſerint parum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertum.</hi> Your <hi>Catechumeniſts</hi> were either ſuch as were <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> children, vvho vvere to be taught before Baptiſme, as vve are to teach <hi>Blackemores</hi> before Baptiſme, yet this makes nothing againſt our <hi>Infants</hi> Baptiſme; or elſe your <hi>Catechumeniſts</hi> vvere of ſuch as vvere groſely tainted with the error of the <hi>Novatians,</hi> miſtaking the ſenſe of the Scripture, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that the Ancients did ſprinkle in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> it is evident to me by their <hi>clinici,</hi> which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32778:22"/>vvere they that vvere Baptized in their Beds neare the time of their death, vvhich could not be by dipping, but ſprinkling. Now that there vvere ſuch <hi>clinici, Cyprian</hi> ſhewes in his 76. Epiſtle vvritten <hi>ad Magnum;</hi> this may be ſeen likewiſe in other ancient Fathers, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and <hi>Baſilius,</hi> beſides the Councels, all cited by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oſſius</hi> in his fift <hi>Theſis</hi> of the twelfth Diſputation of Baptiſme. That <hi>Constantine</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and <hi>Nectarius,</hi> and <hi>Gregory Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and the like deferred their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, it vvas not becauſe they vvere <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Infants</hi> Baptiſme, but becauſe they vvere rather <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatians,</hi> conceiting that if they ſinned after Baptiſme, they could not be ſaved, and therefore delayed Baptiſme as long as they could, which ſinne of delaying Baptiſme <hi>Tertullian li. de peniten. c.</hi> 6: ſaith is <hi>delinquendi commeatum faceri;</hi> and <hi>Nazianzen Orat.</hi> 40. pag. 643. <hi>Edit. Morell.</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> As for <hi>Grotius</hi> though he was learneder then you, yet he vvas erroneous as you, more fit to live amongſt the <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvanians,</hi> who deny the Trinity, the Diety of Chriſt and Infants Baptiſme, then to be amongſt Orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines. <hi>Grotius</hi> is well known to incline too much to <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Arminians, Anabaptists,</hi> and any thing that is naught.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Where you ſay, there is no antiquity in the firſt three hundred years after Chriſt for <hi>Infants</hi> Baptiſm; let us try it out a little: but firſt, where ſome ſaid that <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> was againſt <hi>Infants</hi> Baptiſme. <hi>Pelagius</hi> denies it, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32778:22"/>was aſhamed of it, though you be not; as in his Epiſtle <hi>ad Innocentium,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> in that clears him, <hi>Cap.</hi> 17. <hi>de peccat. originis.</hi> But now we ſhall ſhew <hi>Infants</hi> Baptiſme before <hi>Pelagius</hi> his time I paſs by <hi>Dioniſius Areopagita,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed he, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. laſt, in his laſt Chapter <hi>Hierarchiae Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticae,</hi> becauſe I ſuſpect him ſpurious. <hi>Hyginus</hi> lived in <hi>Polycarps</hi> time, who was the Apoſtle <hi>Johns</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and was for the Baptiſme of <hi>Infants,</hi> who is ſaid to be the firſt that appointed for <hi>Infants</hi> in Baptiſme <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimos,</hi> and <hi>Patrimas. Lactantius</hi> who is ſaid to live about two hundred yeares of Chriſt, he is for us, <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4. and <hi>Cyprian</hi> who lived within two hundred years of Chriſt is for us, for he heard <hi>Tertullian</hi> (ſaith <hi>Helvicus</hi>) being Biſhop of <hi>Carthage. Anno</hi> 247. He in his <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 59. <hi>ad Fidum,</hi> together with a whole Councell in his time, is for <hi>Infants</hi> Baptiſme: the Councell conſiſted of ſixty ſixe Biſhops, where the Queſtion was, Whether <hi>Infants</hi> might be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized before they were eight dayes old; <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and the Councell held that <hi>Infants</hi> might be Baptized before they were eight dayes old; their Adverſaries held that they might not till the eight dayes were expired. The place in <hi>Cyprian</hi> is cited to be in his Epiſtle, <hi>ad Fidum,</hi> 3. <hi>li.</hi> 8. <hi>Epiſt. Irenaeus</hi> alſo is cited for <hi>Infants, li.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 39. and he lived in <hi>Polycarpus</hi> time. Likewiſe <hi>Origen,</hi> who lived within two hundred and thirty years of Chriſt, in the 5. <hi>l. c.</hi> 6. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 543. <hi>edit. Baſil.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eccleſia traditionem ab Apoſtolis ſuſcepit, etiam parvulis dare Baptiſmum &amp;c.</hi> which is, the Church hath reccived it from the Apoſtles, even to give Baptiſme to <hi>Infants.</hi> The like he hath in the eight Book, and eight Hom. upon <hi>Levit.</hi> And <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> vvho lived not much above three hundred years after Chriſt. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>De Abraham Patriarcha,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nec ſenex proſelytus, nec infans vernaculus excipitur, quia omnis aetas peccato obnoxia, &amp; ideo
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32778:23"/>omnis aetas Sacramento idonea;</hi> and a little after, <hi>Nullum excipit, non infantem;</hi> of the ſame minde is <hi>Cyrillus Hieroſoly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitanus Catech. Myſtag.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; Baſilius exhortat. ad Bapt.</hi> And <hi>Chryſoſtome Hom. ad Neophytos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Chriſtians who were converted by <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle in <hi>Crangonore</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> they have to this day continued the Baptiſing of <hi>Infants,</hi> witneſs <hi>Oſorius,</hi> 3. <hi>l. de rebus geſtis Emanuelis,</hi> though for the moſt part they delay it till the children be forty dayes old. <hi>Tertullian</hi> (ſaith <hi>Helvicus</hi>) wrote his Book of <hi>Preſcriptions,</hi> about the year 195. ſome ninty ſeven years after the Apoſtle <hi>Johns</hi> death, at which time he was at leaſt between thirty and forty years old, and ſo borne ſome ſixty years after the Apoſtles death, he (<hi>lib. de Baptiſ. c.</hi> 18.) though he gives ſome frivolous reaſons why <hi>Infants</hi> ſhould not be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, yet therein he clearly ſhews that the people did Baptize their <hi>Infants.</hi> Moreover <hi>Tertullian</hi> was for the neceſſity of Baptiſm to ſalvation, and for the ſalvation of <hi>Infants,</hi> and therfore could not be altogether againſt <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> Baptiſme: but within four or five hundred years of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for <hi>Infants</hi> we find <hi>Jerome Epiſt. ad Laetam,</hi> and towards the end of his third Book againſt the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> where he brings in the Authority of <hi>Cyprian</hi> and his <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagues.</hi> We finde alſo <hi>Innocentius, Epiſt.</hi> 26. to the <hi>Milevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> Councell. And <hi>Auguſtinus, Epiſt.</hi> 28 <hi>&amp; de peccat. orig. cap.</hi> 40. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>li. de nuptiis &amp; concup. cap.</hi> 20. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de peccat. mer. &amp; remiſſi. cap.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>lib. contra Jul. &amp;</hi> 4. <hi>li. de Bapt. contra Donatiſt. cap.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>And we finde <hi>Paulinus</hi> for <hi>Infants in vita Ambroſii; &amp; Theodoret Epitome divinorum dogmat. cap. de Baptiſmo; &amp; Leo Magnus, Epiſt.</hi> 84. <hi>aliis</hi> 86 <hi>ad Epiſc. Aquileienſ.</hi> And the Writer <hi>de vocat. gentium lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. And <hi>Gennadius de Eccl. Dogm. cap.</hi> 31. All theſe for <hi>Infants</hi> Baptiſme lived
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32778:23"/>within the firſt five hundred years after Chriſt; yea whole Councels beſides, that in <hi>Cyprians</hi> time were for them, as the Councell of <hi>Carthage</hi> called the <hi>Milevitan</hi> held <hi>Anno</hi> 418. in the 2. <hi>Canon</hi> thus, <hi>Quicunque parvulos recentes ab uteris matrum Baptizandos negat, aut dicit in remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem quidem peccatorum cos Baptizari, ſed nihil ex Adam trahere originalis peccati quod regenerationis lavacro expietur, Anathema ſit:</hi> And the Councell at <hi>Gerund</hi> held <hi>Anno</hi> 517. in the fift Canon is to the ſame purpoſe, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the ſecond Councel at <hi>Bracara</hi> in the ſeventh Canon; laſtly, the Councell at <hi>Vienna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will here cloſe with ſome places of <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> And firſt, <hi>De Geneſi ad liter am l.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 23: <hi>Conſuetudo (inquit) matris Eccleſiae in Baptizandis parvulis nequaquam ſpernenda eſt, neque ullo modo ſuperflua deputanda, nec omnino tradenda niſi Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae eſſet traditio,</hi> where he means <hi>traditionem</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as appears <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Baptiſ. cap.</hi> 24. where he proves it by Scripture againſt the <hi>Donatifis:</hi> his words likewiſe <hi>li.</hi> 1. <hi>de peccat mer. &amp; remiſſi. cap.</hi> 26. are; <hi>parvulos Baptizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos eſſe</hi> Pelagiani <hi>concedunt, qui contra authoritatem univerſae Eccleſiae proculdubio per Dominum &amp; Apostolos traditam veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non: poſſunt &amp; Ser.</hi> 10. <hi>de verbis Apoſtoli. Ne, mo inquit, vohis ſuſurret doctrinas alienas: hoc Eccleſia ſemper habuit, ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per tenuit, hoc a majorum fide accepit, hoc uſque in finem perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranter cuſtodit. Idem lib.</hi> 2. <hi>contra Caeleſt. &amp; Pelag.</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Caeleſtin.</hi> himſelf in a Book ſet forth at <hi>Rome,</hi> confeſſed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants <hi>Baptizari in remiſſionem peccatorum ſecundum regulam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſae Eccleſiae &amp; ſecundum Evang lu ſertentiam.</hi> To this ſame purpoſe, <hi>Aug. de peccat. Orig ca.</hi> 17. And <hi>de Baptiſ. contra Donatiſt. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 23. If any man aske Divine Authority on this matter, although we moſt rightly believe, ſaith he, that what the Univerſall Church holdeth, and was not inſtituted by Councells, but hath been ever held, was
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32778:24"/>not delivered but by Apoſtolicall Authority, yet may we truly conjecture what the Sacrament of Baptiſme perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to Infants by Circumciſion, which the former peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did receive; <hi>&amp; de pec. Merit. &amp; remiſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. All Antiquity hath firmely held, that believers Infants do receive remiſſion of originall ſin by Baptiſme. <hi>Origen. Hom.</hi> 8. <hi>in Levit. quid cauſae eſt cum Baptiſmus Eccleſiae in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionem peccatorum detur, ſecundum Eccleſiae obſervantiam etiam parvulis Baptiſmus detur? Ita Hom.</hi> 14. <hi>in Luc. &amp; lib.</hi> 5. <hi>in cap.</hi> 6. <hi>ad Rom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Justine Martir</hi> lived in the Apoſtle <hi>Johns</hi> time, and ſaith, women ought to look<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to their children, for of ſuch is the Kingdome of Heaven; And <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen Orat.</hi> 40. <hi>pag.</hi> 658. which was concerning holy <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Finally, Where you cloſe with your ſervice, I know no ſervice of yours, except it be wherein you are more fit to ſerve then I to ſuffer; nevertheleſs to pray for your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and to do you good I am yours,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Alexander Kellie.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:32778:24"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Anabaptists</hi> think and ſay, that there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for <hi>Infants</hi> Baptiſme, being ſuch as do not underſtand, nor make confeſſion of faith or ſins, and yet we give them Scripture commands, many and full, though nothing will ſatisfie them, no not when they have good meaſure, preſſed downe, ſhaken together, and running over; as <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. there is not only a command for <hi>Infants</hi> that cannot confeſs, but a reaſon that ſtill holds, to wit, that the Lord is their God, and God threatens the diſobedient, and this command in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials was never abrogated. Therefore here is the firſt Command, with a full perpetuall reaſon, and with a threatning, and a command of a continuall ſtanding, and is the very ſame with Baptiſme in the eſſentialls</p>
            <p n="2">2. When Chriſt commands <hi>Infants</hi> to be brought to him, to bleſs them, to pray for them, to lay his hands on them, therein he commands as much and more then Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme comes to: So here is a ſecond command, running over with the wrath of Chriſt to them that oppoſe it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. <hi>Baptize all Nations,</hi> is a command likewiſe of a full meaſure running over, for it doth not only reach <hi>Infants,</hi> but all Nations.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>Peter</hi> commands every one to be Baptized, with a reaſon reaching <hi>Infants,</hi> for theirs is the Promiſe, and here againe you have both Precept, and Promiſe: and yet the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> ſaith, there is no command. What is it to ſet the Word of God at naught, and to caſt his Commandements behinde our back, if this be none? Let ſuch therefore take heed leſt the Lord come and teare
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32778:25"/>them in peeces, while there ſhall be none to deliver. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>John Leydan</hi> and ſuch fellows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infants</hi> have all the graces ſet forth and ſealed in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, therefore are to be Baptized, they are juſtified ſanctified, regenerated, clothed with Chriſt, planted with him, added to the Church, incorporate in his body, entitled in the Covenant to have the Lord for their God, dead, buried, and riſen againe with him, and had by Gods command for many hundreth years a right to an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance equivalent to Baptiſme, being then profitable eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way, and the ſeale of the righteouſneſs of Faith, and were never ſince put aſide from Baptiſme, but by that wofull generation of <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> here of late ſince the beginning of <hi>Luthers</hi> oppoſing the Pope; ſince which time the Lord hath fearfully blaſted that wicked ſort of people in many Nations. And therefore I conclude, that children in their Infancie have an undoubted, full and clear right from Scripture for their Baptiſme ſtill to this day, and ſhall have till the laſt day, when the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſhall be judged and convinced to purpoſe of all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly deeds and ſpeeches which they have done and ſpoken againſt Chriſts Truth. And as for the particular graces that I have named, as Juſtification of <hi>Infants,</hi> ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall, God willing, if I be put unto it, eaſily prove all theſe graces to belong to <hi>Infants</hi> in our dutifull and charitable judgement againſt any <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> in <hi>England</hi> whoſoever he be.</p>
            <p>I could wiſh with all my heart that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> would weigh well and conſider what I write without prejudice, remembring that it is no ſhame for them to forſake their errour, but rather their honour and happineſs to turne to the Truth, and ſtand for it, and it is both their ſhame
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32778:25"/>and ſin to be hardned in their hearts againſt it. Better then they have forſaken this error and cloſed with us, <hi>Zuinglius</hi> who farr excelled all the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in the world both for grace and learning; Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who may be a patterne for holineſs and reading to moſt of his time, he hath not only forſaken the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> but oppoſed them, that they are not all able to anſwer him. There be many <hi>Engliſh</hi> Books of learned men aganſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> as namely Doctor <hi>Featly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Marſhall,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gerce,</hi> Mr. <hi>Church,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cobbet,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cooke,</hi> Mr: <hi>Blake,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fuller.</hi> Mr. <hi>Sidenham;</hi> beſides many other excellent men, who have written in <hi>Latine,</hi> as <hi>Voſſius, Calvin, Beza, Bullinger,</hi> and all our beſt Lights in the Chriſtian world, both Ancient and Moderne.</p>
            <p>Theſe five ſheets do not, and cannot containe the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth part of what I have delivered to my Hearers, for the ſpace almoſt of three years, for Infants, and againſt <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and much more may be ſaid.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
